The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki;
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Dear Brothers and Sisters,
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
This is our second session of the Madina series, Part Two.
We're talking about the last five years of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina.
We talked last session about some events that occurred between Al-Khandaq(ألخندق) and Ghazwa-Tul-Hudaybiyyah(غزوةالحديبيه).
So we carry on now we're in the six year of Hijrah(هجرة)
and Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) starts this year with mentioning Ghazwat Zee Qarad(غزوة زي قَرَد) or Ghazwat Al-Ghabaa(غزوة الغابه).
This story has been mentioned by Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ), Muslim(مسلم) Al-Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ)
and also Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) mentioned it, so there's various narrations for this story
and I'll read you the one by Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) which is here in Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر)
and I'll translate it as I read it.
وَقَالَ اِمَامُ اَحْمَدْ حَدَّثَنَا هَاشِمْ اِبْنِ القَاسِمْ حَدَّثّنا عِكْرِمَة بِنْ عَمَّارْ حَدَّ ثَّنِيْ اِيَّاس بِنْ سَلَمَهْ بِنْ اَكْوَعْ عَنْ اَبِيْهِ قَالْ
قَدِّمْنَا الْمَدِيْنَةَ فِيْ زَمَنَ الْحُدَيْبِيَةْ
مَعَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فَخَرَجْتُ اَنَا وَرَبَاْح
غُلَامً النَّبِيْ صلى الله عليه وسلم بِظَهْرِ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وَخَرَجْتُ بِفَرَسِ لِّطَلْحَةَ بِنْ عُبَيْدِ الله ، كُنْتُ اُرِيْدُ اَنْ اُنَدِّيَّه’ مَعَ الْاِبِلْ
Al-Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) narrates from Salamah Ibn Akwah(سَلَمَهْ بِنْ اَكْوَعْ) that,
he along with one of the slaves of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Rabbah(رباح),
they went out of Madina for the camels to graze
and it mentions in, another narration by, I think it's by Al-Waqidee(الواقدي)
that they used to take them first to a place called Bay'yaaz(بياض),
and then that area ran out of pasture.
So, they had to move further on to a place called the Al-Ghaabah(ألغابه), in order, for the camels to graze.
And Salamah(سلمه), he wasn't with the camels of Rasool Allahﷺ, I mean he wasn't appointed as shepherd,
it was Rabbah(رباح), who was the shepherd but Salamah(سلمه), he went out
because he had the horse of Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله),
Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله) is one of Al-Muhajireen(المهاجرين)
one of the 10 who are given the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة).
And Salamah Ibn Akwah(سَلَمَهْ بِنْ اَكْوَعْ) is also a Muhajir(مهاجر), although he's not from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
See you have Muhajireen(المهاجرين) and Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
Who are Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).?
Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) are Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألأوس ولخزرج) that's it.
There's no other Ansaar(ألأنصار),
Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) are two tribes,
two tribes make up Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), it's only these two tribes.
It is Al-Aos(إلأوس) and Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج)
and these, two tribes our brethren in terms of genealogy,
فِي شجرة النسب
Ya'ani(يعني) they are from the same descendents of Al-Azd(ألأزد)
and Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) are everyone else who made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina
the most important group of Al-Muhajireen(ألمهاجرين), obviously are Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
the tribe of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر), Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله), Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدبن ابي وقاص),
Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(ابوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح), Saeed Bin Zaid(سعيدبن زيد),
all of these are from the Al-Muhajireen(ألمهاجرين) from Makkah.
But then you had Muhajireen(ألمهاجرين) from other tribes also
you had from Bannu Sulaim(بنو سُلَيْم),
you had from Ghaffar(غِفار) for example Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبو ذر إلغفاري).
Ghifaar(غفار) are Bedouin tribes in Hijaaz(حجاز),
and Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari(أبو ذر الغفاري) was Muhajir(مهاجر) from there,
then you have Abu Musa Al-Ashari(أبو موسى ألأشعري) is also considered the Mohajer(مهاجر), he came from Yemen.
So, all of these people who came from outside Madina are called Muhajireen(مهاجرين).
So, Salamah Ibn Akwah(سَلَمَهْ بِنْ اَكْوَعْ), he is a Mohajer(مهاجر) but he's not from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was serving some of the other Sahabah رضي الله عنهم he was working for Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله),
he would take out his horse for it, to go out and graze on, the pasture outside of Al-Madina.
And they had to leave early in the day,
another narration it says, that they left before Fajar(فجر) before the first Aadhan(آذان),
so very early on, in the day they had to go out.
Regarding the camels of Rasool Allah ﷺ, they would leave early in the day
and they would come back at the time of Maghrib(مغرب) and then they would milk them and have their dinner.
فَلَمَّا كَانَ بِغَلَسٍ اَغَارَ عَبْدالرحمن بن عُيَيْنَهْ عَلى اِبِلِ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فَقَتَلَ رَاعِيْهَا وَخَرَجَ   يَطْرُدُهَا هُوَ وَاُنَاْس مَعَه’ فِيْ الْخَيْلَ
When it was Ghalas(غلس), Ghalas(غلس) is the time of Fajar(فجر) but it's still dark
Abdur Rahman Ibn Uyaynah(عبدالرحمن إبن عيينه) and these are from the tribe of Ghatafaan(غطافان)
they attacked and they stole the camels of Rasool Allah ﷺ and they killed, the shepherd.
وَخَرَجَ   يَطْرُدُهَا هُوَ وَاُنَاْس مَعَه’ فِيْ الْخَيْلَ فَقُلْتُ: يَا رباح
اُقْعُدْ عَلى هَذَا الْفَرَسْ فَالْحِقْه’ بِطَلْحَه،
وَاَخْبِرْ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اَنَّه’ قَدْ اُغِيْرَ عَلى سَرْحِهْ
قَال: وَقُمْتُ عَلى تَلٍّ فَجَعَلْتُ اوَجْهِيْ مِنْ قِبَلِ الْمَدِيْنَةْ ،
ثُمَّ نَادَيْتُ ثَلَاثَ مَرَّاتْ: يَا صُبْاحَاهْ
قال: ثُمَّ اَتْبَعْتُ الْقَوْمَ مَعِيْ سَيْفِيْ وَنَبْلِيْ
فَجَعَلْتُ اَرْمِيْهِمْ وَاَعْقَرْبِهِمْ،وَذَالِكَ حِيْنَ يَكْثُرُ الشَّجَرَ
Salama(سلمه) said: So, I told Rabbah(رباح) take this horse and go back to Madina
and deliver to Talha Bin Obaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله)
and let Rasool Allah ﷺ know that his camels have been taken away.
Salama رضي الله عنه, rather than taking the horse himself, he gave it to Rabbah(رباح),
in order to take it back to Madina, and he depended on his own legs,
he was a very fast runner.
So, he wanted the news to get back to Madina very fast.
So, he sent Rabbah(رباح) with his horse, but he, himself he climbed over a small mountain or on top of the hill
and then he cried
وَصُبْاحَاهْ، وَصُبْاحَاهْ، وَصُبْاحَاهْ
three times Wa-Subhaa(وَصُبْاحَاه) is the call of emergency
it's like 911 there's something urgent and there's an emergency
that is, what you say and it's especially said, when an army has attacked, you say Wa-Subhaa(وَصُبْاحَاه)
and that is the call that Rasool Allah ﷺ, made
when he wanted to announce to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) the message.
So when a person calls Wa-Subhaa(وَصُبْاحَاه) people are definitely going to come and listen to him.
Salamah Ibn Akwah(سَلَمَهْ بِنْ اَكْوَعْ) he stood on the mountain on this hill
and he called Wa-Subhaa(وَصُبْاحَاه) and his voice was heard in Madina
and that is when the men were calling and saying when they heard his call,
they were saying,
يَا خَيْلَ اللهِ الرْكَبِيْ
And this was the first time this slogan was used.
O, horses of Allah  ride on.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) responded to the call very fast and they came rushing towards Rasool Allahﷺ,
when they heard the call of Salamah(سلمه).
Now Salamah(سلمه) himself after that he followed Abdur Rahman Ibn Uyaynah(عبدالرحمن إبن عيينه),
and he said; I had with me my sword, and my bow and arrow.
فَجَعَلْتُ اَرْمِيْهِمْ وَاَعْقَرْبِهِمْ
And I would shoot at them and,
وَاَعْقَرْبِهِمْ،
Means I would kill their horses, he would target the horses and kill the horses
وَذَالِكَ حِيْنَ يَكْثُرُ الشَّجَرَ
And I would do that when there would be a lot of trees because he could ambush them.
And he could also take a position of hiding that to protect him.
فَاِذَا رَجَعَ اِلَيَّ فَارِسٌ جَلَسْتُ لَه’ فِيْ اَصْلِ شَّجَرَةْ، ثُمَّ رَمَيْتَ
فَلَا يُقْبِلْ عَلَيَّ فَارِسٌ اِلَّا عَقَرْتُ بِهْ
فَجَعَلْتُ اَرْمِيْهِمْ، وَاَنَا اَقُوْلْ : اَنَا اِبْنِ الْاَكْوَعْ، وَالْيَوْم يَوْمُ الرُّضَّعْ
He said: I would shoot them, when I would be in between trees.
And whenever, one of their horsemen would come back to me
I would hide for him, behind the tree, and I would shoot at him,
while I would call out to them, the Battle Cry of
خُذْهَا وَاَنَا اِبْنِ الْاَكْوَعْ وَالْيَوْم يَوْمُ الرُّضَّعْ
This is a line of poetry that he made.
It says; Take it!
I am Ibn-Al-Aqwa(ابن الاكوع), I'm the son of Al-Aqwa(اكوع), today the wicked will die.
اَلْيَوْم يَوْمُ الرُّضَّعْ
Means today the wicked will die and he would repeat on this battle cry again and again.
فَاِذَا كُنْتُ فِيْ الشَّجَرْ اَحْرَقْتُهُمْ بِالْنَبَلْ ،
فَاِذَا تَضَايَقَتِ الثَّنَايَا عَلَوْتُ الْجَبَلَ فَرَدَيْتُهُمْ بِالْحِجَارَةْ
فَمَا زَالَ ذَالِكَ شَاْنِيْ وَشَاْنُهُمْ اَتَّبِعُهُمْ وَارْتَجِزْ،
حَتَّى مَا خَلَقَ اللهُ شَيْئاً
مِنْ ظَهَرِ رسول االه صلى الله عليه وسلم اِلَّا خَلَّفْتَه’ وَرَاَءْ ظَهْرِيْ
He said: When I would be in the trees,
اَحْرَقْتُهُمْ بِالْنَبَلْ
I would burn them with my arrows.
And if we come through mountain passes narrow trails in the mountain,
I would climb on top of them and throw them with rocks.
So, Salama Ibn Al-Akwa رضي الله عنه was driving these men crazy.
I mean, he's alone and he's fighting this entire group of men.
So, first of all, he's alone and they are a large group.
Number two, he was on foot and they were on horseback.
But Salamah(سلمه) was courageous and he was fast, and he was a good Archer.
And, the most important of all, he was a Mo'min(مؤمن).
He said: Everything that they have taken away, I left it behind my back.
These men were running away from Salamah(سلمه)
and to make themselves light and faster in running away from him.
They left behind the camels and then they started in fact, leaving behind some of their own belongings.
It says in one narration that they left behind them 30 spears and 30 cloaks, Burad(بُرد)
they had to leave all this behind them, to lighten their weight
and whenever, Salamah(سلمه) would come across something, they would leave
he would put some stones on top of it to mark its location.
حَتَّى إِذَا امْتَدْ الضُّحَى أَتَاهُمْ عُيَيْنَة بِنْ بَدْر اَلْفَزَارِيْ مَدَدَا لَّهُمْ
وَهُمْ فِيْ ثَنِيَّةٍ ضَيِّقَةْ ، ثُمَّ عَلَوْتُ الْجَبَلْ ، فَأَنَا فَوْقَهُمْ
فَقَالَ عُيَيْنَةْ : مَا هَذَا الَّذِيْ أَرَى ؟
قَالُوْا : لَقِيْنَا مِنْ هَذَا الْبَرْحْ
مَا فَارَقَنَا بِسَحَرٍ حَتَّى الْآنْ ، وَأَخَذَ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ فِيْ أَيْدِيْنَا وَجَعَلَه’ وَرَاءَ ظَهْرِهْ
فَقَالَ عُيَيْنَةْ : لَوْلَا أَنَّ هَذَا يَرَى أَنَّ وَرَاَءَهْ طَلَبَا لَّقَدْ تَرَكَكُمْ ، لِيَقُمْ إِلَيْهِ نَفَرُ مِّنْكُمْ
And then, they received reinforcements from Uyayena Bin Badar Al-Fizaari(عيينة بن بدر ألفزاري)
he came to them and they were in a narrow mountain pass.
So, I climbed on top of them.
And then Uyeyena(عيينة) said: What is this that I see?
They said, We have seen such a difficult time from this man.
And then they said: He has not left us since early in the day, until this moment
and he has taken everything away from us,
Uyeyena(عيينة) told them, if this man sees that you are pursuing him, he would not follow you.
Meaning why are you leaving them alone?
You are the ones who are giving him, that chance but pursue him and he will leave you alone.
So, four of them at the command of Uyeyena(عيينة) started climbing up the mountain to go up to Salamahرضي الله عنه.
So, they started climbing the mountain, until they were in his voice range, he said,
فَلَمَّا أَسْمَعْتَهُمْ الصَوْتَ قُلْتَ : أَتَعْرِفُوْنَنِيْ ؟
قَالُوْا : وَمَنْ أَنْت ؟ قُلْتُ : أَنَا اِبْنُ الْأَكْوَعْ
وَالَّذِيْ كَرَّمَ وَجْهِ محمد لَا يَطْلُبْنِيْ رَجُلٌ مِّنْكُمْ فَيُدْرِكْنِيْ وَلَا أَطْلُبُهْ فَيَفُوْتَنِيْ
فَقَالَ رَجُلُ مِّنْهُمْ  اَنَ أَظُنْ
When they were in his voice, he said: You know who I am?
They said: No. He said: I am the son of Al-Aqwa(الأكوع),
in the name of the one, who has honored the face of Muhammadﷺ
none of you would follow me and reach me
and none of you, whom I follow will escape me, if you try to chase me.
If you try to get me, you won't be able to
but if I pursue you I would hunt you down.
One of them said: I think he's right.
And then they descended.
قَالَ : فَمَا بَرِحْتُ مَقْعَدِيْ ذَلِكَ حَتَّى نَظَرْتُ إِلَى فَوَارِسَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
At that time I started seeing the Knights of Rasool Allah ﷺ approaching.
يَتَّخَلَّلُوْنَ الشَّجَرَ
I could see them between the trees.
وَإِذَا أَوَّلُهُمْ اَلْأَخْرَمْ اَلْأَسْدِيْ
The first among them was Akhram Al-Asdi(اَلأخْرم الأسدي) and following him was Abu Qatada(ابوقتادة),
the Faris(فارس) of Rasool Allah ﷺ the knight of Rasool Ullah.
وَعَلى أِثْرِ أَبِيْ قَتَادَةْ اَلْمِقْدَادْ بِنْ اَلْأَسْوَدْ
and after Abu Qatada(ابوقتادة) was Al-Miqdad Ibn Al-Aswad(ألمقداد إبن الأسود).
فَوَلَّى الْمُشْرِكُوْنَ  مُدْبِرِيْنَ
When the polytheist saw that, they ran away.
وَأَنْزِلُ مِنَّ الْجَبَلِ فَآخَذُ عَنَانَ فَرَسِهْ ، فَقُلْتُ : يَا أَخْرَمْ اَنْذِرِ الْقَوْمْ
يَعْنِيْ اِحْذَرْهُمْ - فَإِنِّيْ لَا آمَنْ مِنْ أَنْ يَقْتَطِعُوْكَ ،
فَاتَّئِدْ حتَىَّ يَلْحِقَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وَأَصْحَابُهْ
The first as we said was Akhram Al-Asdi(اَلأخْرم الأسدي), so I came down
and I held on to the reins of his horse
and I told him: O Akhram( أخرم) Be careful from them!
Because I fear that they will cut you off,
because Al-Akhram( الأخرم) was ahead of the rest and he was alone.
And Salamah(سلمه) wanted to warn him that, if you carry on pursuing the Kuffar(كفار) alone
and you don't wait for the rest of the Muslims to follow they would cut you off and surround you.
What was the response of Akhram Al-Asdi(اَلأخْرم الأسدي) he said,
قَالَ يَا سَلَمة ، إِنْ كُنْتَ تُؤْمِنْ بِاللهِ وَالْيَوْمِ الْآخِرْ
وَتَعْلَمْ أَنَّ الْجَنَّةَ حَقّْ وَالنَّارْ حَقّْ فَلَا تَحُلْ بَيْنِيْ وَبَيْنَ الشَّهَادَةْ
He said: O Salamah(سلمه), if you believe in Allah and the last day
and you believe that Jannah(جنة) is true, and Naar(النار) is true
then don't stand between me and martyrdom, Allah-Ho-Akbar(الله اكبر).
Look at the love that Al-Akhram( الأخرم) had for meeting Allahعَزّوجَلّ
he wanted to meet Allahعَزّوجَلّ as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Salamah(سلمه) said;
فَخَلَّيْتُ عَنَّانَ فَرَسِهْ
I let him go.
فَيَلْحِقْ بِعَبْدُ الرحمن بن عيينة وَيَعْطِفُ عَلَيْهِ عبد الرحمن
So, he pursued Abdur Rahman Ibn Uyeyena(عبدالرحمن إبن عيينه),
and Uyeyena(عيينه) turned around, to face him.
فَاخْتَلَفَا طَعْنَتَيْنَ
each one of them stab the other
فَعَقْرَ الْأخرم بِعَبْدُ الرحمن
Al-Akhram(الأخرم) stabbed the horse of Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)
but Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) stabbed him and killed him,
so now the horse of Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was killed and Al-Akhram( الأخرم) was killed.
So Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) now took over the horse of Al-Akhram( الأخرم).
فَتَحَوَّلَ عَبْد الرحمن عَلَى فَرَسِ الْأَخْرَم ، فَيَلْحَقْ أَبُوْ قَتَادَةْ بِعَبْدُ الرحمن فَاخْتَلَفَا طَعْنَتَيْنَ
فَعُقِرَة بِي اَبِي قَتَادَة وَقَتَلَه أَبُوْ قَتَاَدَةْ ، وَتَحَوَّلَ أَبُوْ قَتَادَةْ عَلَى فَرَسِ الْأَخْرَمْ
Now, the opposite happened Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) attacked, Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن)
and in this case it was Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن), who killed the horse, stabbed at the horse of Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) and killed it.
While the Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) stabbed Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) and killed him
so now he took over the horse that Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) had which is originally the horse of Al-Akhram( الأخرم).
ثُمَّ إِنِّيْ خَرَجْتُ أَعْدُوْ فِيْ أَثْرِ الْقَوْمَ
حَتَّى مَا أَرَى مِنْ غُبَارِ صَحَابَةِ النَّبِيْ صلى الله عليه وسلم شَيْئَا
This is amazing here, Salamah(سلمه) said;
And now I started running after the enemies of Allah
until, I could not see from the dust of the companions of Rasool Ullah a thing.
All of the horsemen of Rasool Allah ﷺ were now behind Salamah(سلمه) while Salamah(سلمه) was running on foot.
وَيُعْرِضُوْنَ قَبْلَ غَيْبُوْبَةِ الشَّمْسَ إِلَى شِعْبٍ فِيْهِ مَاءْ يُقَالُ لَه ذُوْ قَرَدْ
فَأَرَادُوْا أَنْ يَشْرَبُوْا مِنْه’ ، فَأَبْصَرُوْنِيْ أَعْدُوْ وَرَاءَهُمْ فَعَطَفُوْا عَنْه’
So, now it was almost Maghrib(مغرب) time, sunset
and they reached to a valley that had some water in it.
It's called Zou Qarad(ذوقرد) and they wanted to drink from that water
but when they saw me running after them, pursuing them they left it
and they started running up the hills.
وَغَرَبَتِ الشَّمْسَ ، وَأَلْحَقُ رَجُلْ فَأَرْمِيْهَ
And now the sun has set, so I followed one of them and I struck him, with an arrow and I told him,
خُذْهَا وَاَنَا اِبْنِ الْاَكْوَعْ وَالْيَوْم يَوْمُ الرُّضَّعْ
So, he repeated, his battle cry, take it, I am the son of Al-Aqwa(الأكوع),
today the wicked will die, whay did that man say?
فَقَالَ : يَا ثَكْلَ أُمَّ أَكْوَعْ بُكْرَةْ
He said: Woe to your mother, are you the Aqwa(أكوع) of this morning.?
I mean are you the same man who has been following us since the beginning of the day.?
فَقُلْتَ : نَعْمَ
I said yes,
أَيّ عَدُّوَّ نَفْسَهْ
You enemy of yourself!
وَكَانَ الَّذِيْ رَمَيْتَه’ بُكْرَةْ وَأَتْبَعْتَه’ سَهْمًا آخَرْ فَعَلِقَ بِهْ سَهْمَانْ
And this happened to be a man whom I have already struck with an arrow in the morning,
so now he had two arrows sticking out of him.
وَيَخْلُفُوْنَ فَرَسَيْنَ فَجِئْتُ بِهِمَا أَسُوْقَهُمَا
إِلَى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وَهُوَ عَلَى الْمَاءْ اَلَّذِيْ أَجْلَيْتُهُمْ عَنْه
ذُوْ قَرَدْ - وَإِذَا بِنَبِيُ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فِيْ خَمْس مِائَةْ
وَإِذَا بِلَالْ قَدْ نَحَرَ جَزُوْرَا مِمَّا خَلَّفْتَ ،
فَهُوَ يَشْوِيْ لِرَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مِنْ كَبدِهَا وَسَنَامِهَا
He said: They left behind them two horses, so I took them over
and now I went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I found them sitting on the same well or water
that was in this valley which the Mushrikeen(مشركين) wanted to drink from
and I found Rasool Allah ﷺ with 500 men
and Bilal(بلال) was slaughtering for them one of the camels that I have left behind me
and he was roasting part of its liver and it's meaning
كَبدِهَا وَسَنَامِهَا
And he was roasting for them from this camel
and I came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him.
يا رسول الله ، خَلِّنِيْ فَأَنْتَخِبُ مِنْ أَصْحَابِكَ مِائَةْ ، فَآخَذْ عَلَى الْكُفَّارِ بِالْعَشْوَةْ ، فَلَا يَبْقَى مِنْهُمْ مُخْبِرْ إِلَّا قَتَلْتَه
O Rasool Ullah, let me choose 100 from amongst your men
and I would pursue with them, the Kuffar(كفار), until we'll leave none of them alive.
فَقَالَ : " أَكُنْتَ فَاعِلٍا ذَلِكَ يَا سَلَمْةَ ؟
would you do so, O Salamah(سلمه).
قُلْتُ : نَعَمْ
I said: Yes.
وَالَّذِيْ أَكْرَمَكْ
In the name of Allah, who has honored you,
Rasool Allah ﷺ laughed, until I saw his teeth from the light of the fire.
ثُمَّ قَالْ : إِنَّهُمْ يَقْرَوْنَ الْآنْ بِأَرْضِ غَطَفَان
Now, they are already being fed in the land of Ghatafaan(غطفان).
A man came from Ghatafaan(غطفان) and said:
مَرُّوْا عَلَى فُلَانْ الغطفاني، فَنَحْرَ لَهُمْ جَزُوْرًا
They passed by certain men from Ghatafaan(غطفان), so he slaughtered for them a camel
فَلَمَّا أَخَذُوْا يَكْشَطُوْنَ جِلْدَهَا رَأَوْا غَبَرَةْ ، فَتَرَكُوْهَا وَخَرَجُوْا هِرَابًا
And when they started skinning the camel,
they saw some dust, so they left it and ran away
they thought that this is Rasool Allah ﷺ and his companions
so they didn't even enjoy their meal.
When it was morning of the next day, Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
خَيْرُ فُرْسَانِنَا الْيَوْم أبو قتادة ، وَخَيْرُ رَجَّالَتِنَا سَلَمَة
The best of our horseman today, is Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة)
and the best of our foot soldiers is Salamah(سلمه).
فَأَعْطَانِيْ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سَهْمٌ الفَارِسْ وَالرَاجُلْ جَمِيْعَا
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave me spoils of war equal to that of a knight and a foot soldier together.
ثُمَّ أَرْدَفَنِيْ وَرَاءَهُ عَلَى الْعَضْبَاءْ رَاجِعِيْنَ إِلَى الْمَدِيْنَةَ
And he had me ride with him on his Camel, Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء),
until when we were going back to Madina.
فَلَمَّا كَانَ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَهُمْ قَرِيْبَ مِنْ ضَحْوَةْ
When we were close to Al-Madina.
وَفِي الْقَوْمِ رَجُلٌ مِنْ اَلْأَنْصَارْ كَانَ لَا يُسْبَقْ جَعَلَ يُنَادِيْ
فَلَمَّا كَانَ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَهُمْ قَرِيْبَ مِنْ ضَحْوَةْ
When we were close to Al-Madina and Dhahwa(ضَحْوَةْ) is
something like around half a day distance or something like that.
وَفِي الْقَوْمِ رَجُلٌ مِنْ اَلْأَنْصَارْ كَانَ لَا يُسْبَقْ
And amongst us, was a man from an Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), who was not defeated in racing
فَجَعَلَ يُنَادِيْ : هَلْ مِنْ مُسَابِقْ
He would call out, Is there anyone who would race me.?
This was the best among Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), fast runner.
أَلَا رَجُلٌ يُسَابِقْ إِلَى الْمَدِيْنَةْ
Is there anyone who would race me, to Madina?
And we kept on repeating that again and again,
while I am behind Rasool Allah ﷺ so I told him.
أَمَّا تُكْرِمُ كَرِيْمًا وَلَا تَهَابُ شَرِيْفًا
Don't you honor, the honorable and Don't you fear the noble.
He said: No except Rasool Allah ﷺ, What's Salamah(سلمه) meant by that is
I mean, you've been challenging us too much.
Don't you have respect for anyone, obviously he was joking with this Ansaari(اَنصاري)
and saying don't you respect the noble or fear the powerful
so this man said: No, except Rasool Allahﷺ this is the only one, whom I would not challenge.
Tayyab(طيب), when he said that and Salama Ibn Aqwaرضي الله عنه has been running the entire day before
but this challenge was too much for him, to pass on
because this man has been repeating it again and again.
So, he said;
يا رسول الله ، بِأَبِيْ أَنْتَ وَأُمِّيْ ، خَلِّنِيْ فَلَأُسَابِقَ الرَّجُلْ . قَالَ : إِنْ شِئْتَ
So I said O Messenger of Allah
May my father and mother be sacrifice for you.
Let me race this man.
قَالَ : إِنْ شِئْتَ
If you want.
قُلْتَ : اَذْهَبْ إِلَيْكَ . فَطَفَرَ عَنْ رَاحِلَتِهْ وَثَنَيْتُ رِجْلِيْ فَطَفَرْتُ عَنْ النَّاقَةْ
ثُمَّ إِنِّيْ رَبَطْتُّ عَلَيْهِ شَرَفًا أَوْ شَرْفَيْنَ ، يَعْنِيْ اِسْتَبْقَيْتَ مِنْ نَفْسِيْ
ثُمَّ إِنِّيْ عَدَوْتُ حَتَّى أَلْحَقَّهْ ، فَأَصُكْ بَيْنَ كَتِفَيْهِ بِيَدِيْ ، قُلْتَ : سَبَقْتُكَ وَالله
أَوْ كَلِمَةْ نَحْوَهَا . قَالَ : فَضَحِكْ وَقَالَ : إِنْ أَظُنْ . حَتَّى قَدِمْنَا الْمَدِيْنَةْ
So, he said: I'll come to you and at this, he jumped off his mount
and I bent my leg and jumped down from the camel
and then Salama رضي الله عنه let the man get the head of him,
while he was holding himself back because he said
اِسْتَبْقَيْ نَفْسِيْ
He wanted to preserve his breath, so he was allowing this man to be ahead of him for a particular distance,
until we got close to Madina, then I ran hard
and when I was behind him, I slapped him between his shoulders with my hand
and told him; I beat you in the name of Allah,
the man laughed and said: I agreed, so he went into Madina.
So, for the entire race this Ansari(اَنصاري) was ahead of Salamah(سلمه)
but when they were close to Madina, Salamah(سلمه) picked up speed
and then when he was passing next to the Ansari(اَنصاري)
he patted him between his shoulders and told him I beat you by the name of Allah,
the man said;
إِنْ أَظُنْ
You are right.
And this was the fastest runner among Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
but nobody can beat Salama Ibn Aqwa رضي الله عنه.
This is the story of Ghazwat Zee Qarad(غزوة زي قَرَد) or what is called also Ghazwat Al-Ghabaa(غزوة الغابه).
And then Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) talks here about the camel of Rasool Allah ﷺ Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء)
and the story of the Camel Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء) because here we mentioned
that Rasool Allah ﷺ was riding on Al-Adbaa(ألعضباء) and he had Salama رضي الله عنه ride with him.
So, what's the story of Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء)?
Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء) was a very fast Camel
and it belongs to a man from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل)
so how did it end up in the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
This Hadith(حديث) is narrated by Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal رضي الله عنه, it says that;
كَانَتِ الْعَضْبَاءْ :لِرَجُلٍ مِنْ بَنِيْ عَقِيْلْ ، وَكَانَتْ مِنْ سَوَابِقِ الْحَاج
Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء) belong to a man from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل) and it was a racing camel
مِنْ سَوَابِقِ الْحَاج
It was very fast Camel, it was Hajj(حج) racing camel.
This man was taken captive by the Muslims along with his camel.
Rasool Allah ﷺ passed by him, when he was tied up
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was riding on a donkey then
so the man called out to Muhammadﷺ and said;
يَا محمد ، عَلَامَ تَأْخُذُوْنِيْ وَتَأْخُذُوْنِ سَابِقَةِ الْحَاجْ
Why did you take me and take the Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء),
the racing camel of Hajj(حَجْ).
This man from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل) it is protesting, Why was he arrested?
Why was he taken captive?
He was traveling somewhere in Arabia and the Sahabah(صحابه) saw him
and they captured him, and brought him to Madina and they tie him up.
So, now when he saw Muhammadﷺ passing by him, he said: Why have you taken me?
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded back
and this man, the reason why, he was protesting
is because his particular tribe were not in a state of war with the Muslims,
they were not fighting the Muslims, there was no battle between them and the Muslim.
So, why was I taken.
Rasool Allah ﷺ answered back and told him,
نَأْخُذُكَ بِجَرِيْرَةِ حُلَفَائِكَ ثَقِيْفَ
We take you because of the fault of your allies Thaqeef(ثقيف).
Now Thaqeef(ثقيف) were in war with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
up until that moment there were no battles between the Muslims and Thaqeef(ثقيف)
but Thaqeef(ثقيف) were supportive of Quraish(قريش) in their efforts and they were against Islam in general
and we know the story of Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he went to At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف)
because Thaqeef(ثقيف) are the tribe that lives in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف)
and we know what happened to Rasool Allah ﷺ in that journey.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: We have taken captive because of the actions of your allies Thaqeef(ثقيف).
At that particular moment, Thaqeef(ثقيف) have taken two Muslims as captives, you see.
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ has taken this man as captive as a revenge against Thaqeef(ثقيف)
even though, this man himself was not from Thaqeef(ثقيف)
but he was from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل), the allies of Thaqeef(ثقيف).
So, what did the man say, he said: I'm a Muslim.
You see, he said, I'm a Muslim.
What did Rasool Allah tell him.
قَالَ :لَوْ قُلْتَهَا وَأَنْتَ تَمْلِكُ أَمْرَكْ ، أَفْلَحْتَ كُلَّ الفَلَاحْ
He told them, if you said it.
وَأَنْتَ تَمْلِكُ أَمْرَكْ
When you had the authority over yourself, then you would have been very successful.
Meaning if you have said so when you were free
now you are a captive and you're trying to claim that you are Muslim, this would have benefited you before.
The man said:
يا محمد ، إِنِّيْ جَائِعٌ فَأَطْعِمْنِيْ وَإِنِّيْ ظَمْآنٌ فَاسْقِنِيْ
He said: O Muhammad(محمد) I am hungry so feed me and I'm thirsty, so quench my thirst.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
هَذِه حَاجَتِكْ
This is your need.
In this regard, there are rights for the prisoner he's fed and he's provided for.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ told him this is your need, to take, what you need.
Back we have stories in the Battle of Badr(بدر)  that the Ansaarرضي الله عنهم,
when Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Treat the prisoners well.
The Ansaar(انصار) would give the prisoners who are Mushrikeen(مشركين) from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
who came out to fight against Rasool Allah ﷺ they would give them the wheat bread
and they, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) would eat the dates and it's considered that wheat bread is a better quality food.
So, they would give them the bread and they would keep the dates for themselves.
So now Rasool Allah ﷺ told him this is your need, we're not going to prevent you from eating and drinking.
What happened next.
He was used as a ransom for the two Muslims, who were taken prisoner.
However he was not given his Camel back.
Rasool Allah ﷺ took that camel for himself.
So this man from Bannu Aqeel(بنوعقيل) was used in this prisoner exchange.
He was exchanged for the two Muslim prisoners
and Rasool Allah took Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء) for himself
and it was a very fast and good camel.
Now, when the Mushrikeen(مشركين) have taken over camels of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they have also taken with them a Muslim woman from Bannu Ghaffar(بنوغفار)
and whenever they would rest at night they would leave their camels.
فِيْ اَفْنِيَتِهِمْ
In their and this area with them.
So this woman, one night while they were asleep
she started walking towards each camel in order to take it and run away on its back to Madina
but the camel would refuse, Ragha(رغا)
it would make this sound, that the camel makes and until she came to Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء)
and Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء) was silent and when she rode on Al-Adhba'a(ألعضباء).
It was a very
فَكَانَتْ نَاقَةْ ذَلُوْل
it was very well domesticated and very simple to lead.
So, she made Nadhar(نذر) a promise to Allah(عَزّوجَلّ), if Allah saves her on the back of this camel.
She would slaughter this camel for the sake of Allah.
So look at what her promise is.
That this camel that will save her, if she arrives safely to Madina, she would slaughter this camel for the sake of Allah.
Now she did arrive to Madina and she told Rasool Allah ﷺ about her promise.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her.
بِئْسِ مَا جَزِتِهَا
What a bad reward you are rewarding this camel.
This camel has saved you and brought you to Madina, now you want to slaughter it,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told her.
" لَا وَفَاءْ لِنَذْرٍ فِيْ مَعْصِيَةِ الله ، وَلَا فِيْمَا لِا يَمْلِكْ اِبْنِ آدَمْ "
You do not have to fulfill a promise that includes a sin
and you do not have to fulfill a promise
and we're talking about Nadhar(نذر) here not promise with a human being.
If you make Nadhar(نذر) to Allah, promise to Allah also if you don't own a thing
and because he didn't own this camel, this camel belong to Rasool Allah ﷺ
Rasool Ullah told her: Not to sacrifice the camel.
Tayyab(طيب).
Some lessons from these stories that we mentioned so far
First of all in the Ghazwa(غزوة) of Zee Qarad(زي قرد)  we can see the fitness of Salama Bin Aqwa رضي الله عنه
and we can see some of the activities that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم would practice such as running,
Salamah(سلمه) and this man from Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) they had the competition in running
and that was approved by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So the Sahaba رضي الله عنهم were fit and they were strong
and this is part of Edaad(ألعِدَاد) which the Muslims were commanded to do.
The Muslims were told to prepare for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
We can see here that Salama Bin Aqwa رضي الله عنه was pursuing this enemy for an entire day, without tiring out.
In fact, they were getting tired and their beasts were getting tired
because as we mentioned it, in the end of the Hadith(حديث) that they have left behind them two horses.
Why did they leave behind those two horses?
Do you think about that?
Why would they leave behind them two horses and a horse is a very valuable thing in those days, really expensive.
Why would they leave behind a horse, unless they had to?
Because the horse was tired, the horse was tired out.
So they had to leave these two horses behind them.
Salama Bin Aqwa(سلمه ابن اَلْاَكوع) was a very fit Sahabi رضي الله عنه.
From the story of the woman, there's a lesson mentioned by An-Nawwawi(النووي)
and this is regarding the traveling of a woman alone.
يَقُوْلُ اَلنَّوَوِيْ فِيْ هَذَالْحَدِيْثْ
جَوَازُ سَفَرِ الْمرأْة وَحْدَهَا بِلَا زَوْجَ وَلَا مَحْرَمْ
وَلَا غَيْرَهُمَا اِذَا كَا نَ السَفَرَ ضَرُوْرة
اِذَا كَانَ السَفَرَ ضَرُوْرَة، كَلْ هِجْرَهْ دَارِالحَرْبِ اِلَى دَارِ الْاِسْلَامْ
وَ كَا الحَرَبِ مِمَّنْ يُرِيْدُ مِنْهَا فَاحِشَةً وَ نَحْوِيْ ذَالِكْ
وَالنَّهِيْ عَنْ سَفَرِهَا وَحْدَهَا مَحْمُوْلٌ عَلَى غَيْرِ الضَّرُوْرَة
He says in this Hadith(حديث), we can derive the ruling that it is allowed for a Muslim woman,
to travel alone without her husband or without a guardian and without anyone else.
If, it is a necessary travel and this is an important point that he mentions
such as Hijrah(هجرة) from the land of war to the land of Islam.
And such as running away from those who want to sin with her and similar situations
and a Muslim woman is prohibited from traveling alone when there is no necessity in her travel.
So, this would clarify some issues, here the statement by Imam An-Nawwawi رضي الله عنه
clarifies this issue of the traveling a woman.
Sometimes a Muslim woman is in great need of traveling alone and it's a necessity for her.
In this case she is allowed to and he mentions as an example, making Hijrah(هجرة).
Tayyab(طيب) it's also probably beneficial here to talk about the rulings regarding POW's in general
because we have covered a few cases up until this moment of how Muslims treat the POW's.
So we'll summarize it all now because we are already talking about prisoners that were taken in Al-Badr(البدر)
and here we talked about this man from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل).
What is the ruling regarding prisoners of war?
Can they be executed, can they be ransomed
or should they be released, what is it exactly?
Because we have seen that they were treated differently in different situations.
To summarize this point, Ash-Shoukani(الشوكاني) says,
مَذْهَبُ الْجَمْهُوْرْ اَنَّ الْاَمْرَ فِى الْاَسَارَى اَلْكَفَرة مِنْ الرِّجَالْ اِلَى الْاِمَامْ
يَفْعَلُ مَاهُوَ أحظ لِلاِسْلَامِ وَ المُسْلِمِيْنْ
He said, That the Mad'hab(مذهب) of the majority of scholars is that the issue of
disbelieving prisoners of war is up to the Imam(اِمَام).
The men, who are Kuffar(كفار) who are prisoners of war, it is up to the Imam(امام) to do with them
what is the most beneficial for the Muslims.
So, what does this mean?
It means that Number one.
They could be released without any compensation
and the example of this is what Rasool Allah ﷺ did with Abu Azzah(ابوعزة) in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Abu Azzah(ابوعزة) was one of the captives the 70 captives that were taken in the battle of Badr(بدر).
Abu Azzah(ابوعزة), he pleaded to the Messenger of Allah and told him that I have daughters
that are left alone and I don't have any wealth to ransom myself.
So for the sake of my daughters release me and Rasool Allah ﷺ released him,
without asking him for any compensation whatsoever.
He was only released on condition that he doesn't fight against the Muslims again
and he consented to that.
The second option is to ransom them.
And this is what happened with the rest of the prisoners in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
such as Al-Abbas(العباس) they had to pay for their ransom and they were released.
The third option they could be exchanged for Muslim prisoners.
And the example of that is what we just talked about
with this man from Banni Aqeel(بني عقيل) he was exchanged for two Muslim prisoners.
The next option is to be executed
and this is what Rasool Allah ﷺ did with An-Nazr Bin Haris(النضربن الحارث)
and Uqba Bin Abi Moayeet(عقبةبن ابي معيت) in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and Abu Azzah(ابوعزة) when he was arrested again in the battle of Uhud(أحَد).
When he was captured again in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
he has already promised that is not going to fight against Rasool Allah ﷺ
and now he was caught fighting against the Muslims, so he was executed.
And also the entire fighting force of Bannu Quraizah(بنوقريظة), the Jewish tribe
Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered, that they be put to death.
So these are the different options that the Imam(اِمَام) has regarding the Prisoners of War.
Next اِنْ شاءالله تعالى we'll talk about the important event of Al-Hudaybiya(الحديبيه),
so we'll leave that until our next session.
بِاِذْنِ الله عَزُّوجَل
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته